September 11, 2001 Documentary Project Collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
Guides to the Collections in the Archive of Folk Culture
September 11, 2001 Documentary Project Collection 2001-2002
AFC 2001/015
American Folklife Center
47 boxes 33 linear feet 8980 total items in collection 8100 manuscript materials; 386 sound recordings; 421 graphic and photographic materials; 20 moving image items (8 VHS; 9 Compact VHS; 2 mini DV; 1 P6-60); 15 electronic media; 38 artifacts
Archive of Folk Culture, American Folklife Center Library of Congress Washington, D.C. http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.home
Documentation of the reactions of individuals and communities across the United States and elsewhere (Naples, Italy) to the terrorist attacks on the World Trade Center in New York City; the Pentagon in Arlington, Virginia; and the crash of the hijacked plane in Shanksville, Pennsylvania; in audio, video, and photographs from 2001-2002.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
For a list of donating institutions see Appendix A. For a list of where recordings were made see Appendix B.
Organizations
American Folklife Center, collector.; Archive of Folk Culture (Library of Congress); Library of Congress. National Digital Library Program.
Subjects
Memorials--United States.; September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001, in art.; September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001--Interviews.; September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001--Miscellanea.; September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001--Personal narratives.; September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001--Poetry.; September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001--Religious aspects.
Titles
September 11, 2001 documentary project, 2001-2002.
Form/Genre
Children's art.; Drawings.; Flags.; Interviews.; Manuscripts.; Photographs.; Poems.; Scrapbooks.; Sermons.; Sound recordings.; Videocassettes.
Administrative Information
Provenance
On September 12, 2001, the American Folklife Center at the Library of Congress sent an email to folklorists and other ethnographers across the nation asking them to record the thoughts and feelings expressed by individuals and communities following the terrorist attacks of September 11. This project echoes one conducted sixty years earlier, on December 8, 1941, when Alan Lomax, then in charge of the Archive of American Folk Song, sent an urgent telegram to folklorists around the country to collect "man on the street" reactions to the bombing of Pearl Harbor and the subsequent declaration of war by the United States.
Within a week after the September 12 notice was sent, collection materials began to arrive at the Library of Congress. Mail delivery to the Library was abruptly interrupted from October 2001-May 2002, due to the discovery of envelopes containing anthrax in the Hart Senate Office Building, a part of the Capitol complex. During that time, items received via U.S. postal mail were sent offsite to be irradiated in order to rid them of possible anthrax contamination. When the mail delivery to the Library resumed, and collection materials finally began to arrive at the Center, fewer than one percent of items were discovered to be severely damaged or destroyed by the irradiation process. Attempts were made to contact donors of these items and some were able to provide information about the content of their interviews. The destroyed materials remain a part of the collection. Because of the mail delay, donations were accepted through 2002, as long as the materials were reflective of immediate reactions from the fall of 2001.
Access
Access to the collection is unrestricted. Consult a reference librarian in the Folklife Reading Room.
Electronic Format
Significant portions of this collection are available as an American Memory online resource titled September 11, 2001 Documentary Project compiled by the National Digital Library Program of the Library of Congress, http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/collafc.af000016. Selections from this and other Library of Congress September 11 collections can be found in the online exhibit, Witness and Response: September 11 Acquisitions at the Library of Congress, http://www.loc.gov/exhibits/911. A database for the AFC September 11, 2001 collection can also be accessed in the Folklife Reading Room. Consult a reference librarian for additional information pertaining to the website and the database.
Scope and Content Note
On September 12, 2001, the American Folklife Center at the Library of Congress sent a notice to folklorists and ethnographers across the nation asking them to record on audiotape the thoughts and feelings expressed by individuals and communities following the terrorist attacks of September 11, 2001. The project was developed by Ann Hoog, who collaborated with American Folklife Center Director Peggy Bulger in the original call for participation. Materials were mailed to the Library of Congress beginning in September 2001. The collection reflects the regional, ethnic, socioeconomic, and political diversity of Americans at the time of the September 11 attacks.
The collection comprises 8980 items: 8100 manuscript materials; 386 sound recordings (SR); 421 graphic and photographic materials (GR and PH); 20 moving images (MV); 15 electronic media (CF); and 38 artifacts (AR). There are twelve boxes of manuscript materials divided into seven categories: Administrative Materials, Participant Documentation, Unpublished Writings, Reports, Published Works, Internet Folklore, Clippings and Online Articles. These include printout of e-mails, ephemera (from various internet web sites), posters, newspaper articles, personal essays, narratives, children's drawings, and other miscellaneous items that were left at the various memorials.
The Participant Documentation series is arranged in sub-folders (a paper folder within an archival folder) according to the participants' last names and the ID numbers of the materials which pertain to the documentation. This arrangement ensures that the interviewer and the interviewee, and the primary materials (sound recording, photographic images, etc.) are readily identifiable. In some cases, there is no documentation accompanying a specific sound recording, photograph, or other type of medium. Therefore, in some sub-folders there is a "?" after the SR number. This indicates that the documentation most likely goes with that SR number, but the name on the form has not been linked definitively with that particular sound recording. There is a folder entitled "Participant Documentation (Michigan)." Originally there were no tapes accompanying the forms from Michigan State University (MSU). A few irradiated tapes were found which were subsequently linked to Michigan State University (MSU), but could only be identified and not played because of the extensive damage done to the tapes by the irradiation process. The participant documentation is also divided into "originals" and "photocopies" (as there was no way to verify which items had been irradiated, all the documentation was photocopied). All photocopied materials can be served to readers.
There are twenty-two accounts of personal narratives and eleven poetic works within the Unpublished Writings subseries, and they are arranged chronologically. These accounts are the personal experiences of the writers on the day or days following September 11, 2001. Other accounts recall events in the authors' lives months after the attacks.
The Reports subseries consists of school projects that were submitted by several institutions such as Hunter College, Colorado College, and California State University. Each project was approached differently followed prescribed guidelines, which were to capture the thoughts and feelings expressed by the American people in the aftermath of September 11. For example, California State University presented its response in the form of a research project which incorporated the use of posters, overheads, cartoons, and newspaper clippings. The students at Colorado College, on the other hand, wrote term papers based on the interviews they conducted.
The Published Works subseries consists of written articles and statements referring to the events and reactions to the attacks of September 11. The works include excerpts from the Congressional Record, press releases, photographs, flyers, brochures, and other ephemera.
The Internet Folklore section is a compilation of Internet sites that comment on the events of September 11, through humor, images, memorials, legends, and Internet warnings.
The Clippings and Online Articles subseries includes most of the California State University at Chico reports, which contain a large number of newspaper clippings. These clippings are included here and cross-referenced with the reports.
Note that the manuscript materials include database printouts that capture information about sound recordings, graphic and photographic materials, moving images, electronic media, and artifacts, all of which are available on hard copy and on a zip disk located in Box 1, Folder 2.
The Sound Recordings series includes interviews with people who were in the World Trade Center and the Pentagon during the attacks, and also people living in East Sullivan, Maine; Des Moines, Iowa; Los Angeles, California, and many other towns and cities -- small and large -- across the country. Twenty-eight states are represented. The collection includes interviews with teachers and students from elementary to graduate school; police officers, firefighters and other emergency workers; secretaries, executives, librarians, city officials, and people whose families have lived in the United States for generations as well as those recently arrived.
There are approximately 200 interviews from New York City and Arlington, Virginia, but the majority of the interviews in the collection was gathered from other parts of the country. The content of the interviews include views on international relations, politics, economics, patriotism, charity efforts, fears of flying, prejudices, and how relationships were changed by the events of September 11, 2001.
The total number of sound recordings given in the Concordance is accurate as of 2005. Additional items may be added. All of the sound recordings have been duplicated.
The sound recordings database is available in the Folklife Reading Room organized by SR number and alphabetically by the interviewer's last name. The recordings are arranged alphabetically by state, institution of affiliation, interviewer's last name, and interviewee's last name. Using the "find" option in Access, researchers should be able to find a specific sound recording easily. A few sound recordings were added to the collection after the numbering arrangement was completed so the last recording, SR386, is not the final recording. The sound recordings were numbered consecutively regardless of format. Hence, the compact discs are not in sequence. Although the collection of audio recordings was the primary goal of this project, some people documented their community's reactions in photographs. Therefore, this collection also includes photographic documentation of some of the spontaneous memorial tributes created near the Pentagon, and in other parts of the country. These memorials, sign boards, and decorations all reflect the public discourse regarding the events. Candles and flowers, written messages and drawings from children, flags and other items, collectively express the grief and solidarity of individuals and businesses. The American Folklife Center (AFC) staff took photographs of memorials at Arlington Cemetery and near the Pentagon. The American Folklife Center (AFC) also received images from places such as Marietta, Georgia; Knoxville, Tennessee; and Las Vegas, Nevada. The digital graphic images are housed with the electronic media.
Moving Images are arranged alphabetically by state and institution of affiliation. The Moving Image series includes interviews and patriotic songs pertaining to September 11, 2001.
Artifacts are organized by format and institution of affiliation. The artifact collection consists of materials that were gathered from a temporary memorial site in Knoxville, Tennessee or collected as part of a project. They include flags, posters, copper signs, and a sample of the irradiated tapes.
Collection Concordance by Format
Manuscript Materials
112 folders AFC Boxes 1-12
Sound Recordings
386 audiocassettes (original) AFC Boxes 13-34
Photographic Materials
401 images (originals in various sizes) AFC Boxes 35-38, Box 41
Graphic Materials
19 items AFC Boxes 37-38
Moving Images
20 various formats (originals) AFC Boxes 39-40
Electronic Media
15 various formats AFC Box 1, Box 41
Artifacts
38 various formats AFC Boxes 42-47
http://lccn.loc.gov/2005700220
Container List
- SERIES I: MANUSCRIPT MATERIALS (Box 1-12)
  - Administrative Files
    - Collection Guide, 40 pages (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Zip disk (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Contains sound-recordings database, graphic-materials database, moving-images database, electronic-media database, and artifacts database.
    - Sound Recordings Inventory, 62 pages (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Sound recordings organized by ID number (printed copy).
    - Sound Recordings Inventory, 41 pages (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Sound recordings organized alphabetically by the interviewers' last names (printed copy).
    - Graphic Materials Inventory, 19 pages (Box 1, Folder 5)
      (printed copy).
    - Moving Images Inventory, 6 pages (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Electronic Media Inventory, 1 page (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Artifacts Inventory, 1 page (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - September 11, 2001 Documentary Project Website., 6 pages (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Includes a printout of the original call for participation and sample release forms.
    - Certificate of Appreciation, 2 pages (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - E-mail Correspondence, 2001-2002., 18 pages (Box 1, Folder 11)
      E-mail requests for information about the September 11, 2001 Documentary Project Collection.
  - Participant Documentation: Permission Forms, Logs, Surveys, Correspondence
    - Participant Documentation (Originals) (SR001-018), 105 pages (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Participant Documentation (Originals) (SR019-032), 100 pages (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Participant Documentation (Originals) (SR033-070), 75 pages (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Participant Documentation (Originals) (SR071-087), 100 pages (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Participant Documentation (Originals) (SR088-117), 115 pages (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Participant Documentation (Originals) (SR118) (Folder 1 of 2), 50 pages (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Participant Documentation (Originals) (SR118) (Folder 2 of 2), 100 pages (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Participant Documentation (Originals) (SR119) (Folder 1 of 3), 90 pages (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Participant Documentation (Originals) (SR119) (Folder 2 of 3), 105 pages (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Participant Documentation (Originals) (SR119) (Folder 3 of 3), 95 pages (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Participant Documentation (Originals) (SR120-140), 45 pages (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Participant Documentation (Originals) (SR141-162), 95 pages (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Participant Documentation (Originals) (SR163-216), 110 pages (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Participant Documentation (Originals) (SR217-230), 105 pages (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Participant Documentation (Originals) (SR231-257), 105 pages (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Participant Documentation (Originals) (SR258-278), 110 pages (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Participant Documentation (Originals) (SR279-296), 105 pages (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Participant Documentation (Originals) (SR297-318), 125 pages (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Participant Documentation (Originals) (SR319-330), 100 pages (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Participant Documentation (Originals) (SR331-346), 120 pages (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Participant Documentation (Originals) (SR347-359), 110 pages (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Participant Documentation (Originals) (SR360-370), 105 pages (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Participant Documentation (Originals) (SR371-381), 160 pages (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Participant Documentation (Originals) (SR382-386), 140 pages (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Participant Documentation (Originals) (Michigan), 19 pages (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Participant Documentation (Original) (GR01), 1 page (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Participant Documentation (Originals) (PH043-051), (PH283-334), 9 pages (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Participant Documentation (Originals) (PH135-200), (PH201-282), (PH344-401), 45 pages (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Participant Documentation (Originals) (MV01-03), 50 pages (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Participant Documentation (Originals) (MV04-07), 75 pages (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Participant Documentation (Originals) (MV08-10), 20 pages (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Participant Documentation (Photocopies) (SR001-014), 105 pages (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - Participant Documentation (Photocopies) (SR015-026), 120 pages (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Participant Documentation (Photocopies) (SR027-068), 95 pages (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - Participant Documentation (Photocopies) (SR069-070), 65 pages (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Participant Documentation (Photocopies) (SR071-083), 90 pages (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - Participant Documentation (Photocopies) (SR084-098), 100 pages (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - Participant Documentation (Photocopies) (SR099-117), 70 pages (Box 6, Folder 49)
    - Participant Documentation (Photocopies) (SR118) (Folder 1 of 2), 100 pages (Box 6, Folder 50)
    - Participant Documentation (Photocopies) (SR118) (Folder 2 of 2), 100 pages (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - Participant Documentation (Photocopies) (SR119) (Folder 1 of 4), 100 pages (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - Participant Documentation (Photocopies) (SR119) (Folder 2 of 4), 60 pages (Box 6, Folder 53)
    - Participant Documentation (Photocopies) (SR119) (Folder 3 of 4), 60 pages (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - Participant Documentation (Photocopies) (SR119) (Folder 4 of 4), 75 pages (Box 6, Folder 55)
    - Participant Documentation (Photocopies) (SR120-142), 125 pages (Box 7, Folder 56)
    - Participant Documentation (Photocopies) (SR143-162), 110 pages (Box 7, Folder 57)
    - Participant Documentation (Photocopies) (SR163-202), 110 pages (Box 7, Folder 58)
    - Participant Documentation (Photocopies) (SR203-218), 110 pages (Box 7, Folder 59)
    - Participant Documentation (Photocopies) (SR219-230), 110 pages (Box 7, Folder 60)
    - Participant Documentation (Photocopies) (SR231-249), 90 pages (Box 7, Folder 61)
    - Participant Documentation (Photocopies) (SR250-269), 100 pages (Box 8, Folder 62)
    - Participant Documentation (Photocopies) (SR270-286), 100 pages (Box 8, Folder 63)
    - Participant Documentation (Photocopies) (SR287-304), 100 pages (Box 8, Folder 64)
    - Participant Documentation (Photocopies) (SR305-318), 100 pages (Box 8, Folder 65)
    - Participant Documentation (Photocopies) (SR319-327), 85 pages (Box 8, Folder 66)
    - Participant Documentation (Photocopies) (SR328-341), 125 pages (Box 8, Folder 67)
    - Participant Documentation (Photocopies) (SR342-356), 115 pages (Box 9, Folder 68)
    - Participant Documentation (Photocopies) (SR357-368), 125 pages (Box 9, Folder 69)
    - Participant Documentation (Photocopies) (SR369-376), 135 pages (Box 9, Folder 70)
    - Participant Documentation (Photocopies) (SR377-381), 75 pages (Box 9, Folder 71)
    - Participant Documentation (Photocopies) (SR382-386), 140 pages (Box 9, Folder 72)
    - Participant Documentation (Photocopies) (Unknown), 60 pages (Box 9, Folder 73)
      Documentation from Michigan that has not been definitively linked to any sound recording (possibly accompanying one or more of the irradiated tapes in the artifacts section).
    - Participant Documentation (Photocopies) (PH043-051), (PH283-334), (PH135-200), (PH201-282), (PH344-401), 60 pages (Box 9, Folder 74)
    - Participant Documentation (Photocopies) (MV01-03), 90 pages (Box 10, Folder 75)
    - Participant Documentation (Photocopies) (MV04-07) (folder 1 of 2), 100 pages (Box 10, Folder 76)
    - Participant Documentation (Photocopies) (MV04-07) (folder 2 of 2), 60 pages (Box 10, Folder 77)
    - Participant Documentation (Photocopies) (MV08-10), 20 pages (Box 10, Folder 78)
  - Unpublished Writings
    - Personal Narratives, 100 pages (Box 10, Folder 79)
    - Poetry and Lyrics, 75 pages (Box 10, Folder 80)
  - Reports
    - California State University, Chico-Barnard, Molly J., 80 pages (Box 10, Folder 81)
      see also graphic materials in Boxes 34-37.
    - California State University, Chico-Carroll-Perdue, Andrew., 35 pages (Box 10, Folder 82)
      Report by Carroll-Perdue, Andrew.
    - California State University, Chico-Reinschmidt, Michael, 35 pages (Box 10, Folder 83)
      Report by Reinschmidt, Michael;see also clippings/online article in Box 12.
    - California State University-Chico-Valdes, Juan, 65 pages (Box 10, Folder 84)
      Report by Valdes, Juan: see also clippings/online articles, graphic materials in Boxes 12, 34-37.
    - Center for Documentary Studies at Duke University., 22 pages (Box 10, Folder 85)
    - Colorado College-Crisera, Lauren, 5 pages (Box 10, Folder 86)
      Report by Crisera, Lauren
    - Colorado College-Hoecker, Ellie, 45 pages (Box 11, Folder 87)
      Report by Hoecker, Ellie
    - Colorado College-Jansen, Laura, 55 pages (Box 11, Folder 88)
      Report by Jansen, Laura
    - Colorado College-Kaplan, Ann, 65 pages (Box 11, Folder 89)
      Report by Kaplan, Ann
    - Colorado College-McClure, Ted, 15 pages (Box 11, Folder 90)
      Report by McClure, Ted
    - Colorado College-Meehan, Katy, 75 pages (Box 11, Folder 91)
      Report by Meehan, Katy
    - Colorado College-Schoonmaker, Derek, 35 pages (Box 11, Folder 92)
      Report by Schoonmaker, Derek
    - Colorado College-Skyler, Jenni, 50 pages (Box 11, Folder 93)
      Report by Skyler, Jenni
    - Colorado College-Weber, Jarrod, 50 pages (Box 11, Folder 94)
      Report by Weber, Jarrod
  - Published Works
    - Congressional Record (2001 09-12, 2001-09-17), 115 pages (Box 11, Folder 95)
    - Knoxville Writer's Guild, 50 pages (Box 11, Folder 96)
      Contains a press release, administrative information and a list of materials that were a part of "The Wall of Unity, a temporary memorial park.. It was the creation of a group of local artists and developers in Knoxville, Tennessee.
    - Flyers, brochures, and postcards, 30 pages (Box 11, Folder 97)
    - Ephemera EP1-EP3, 3 pages (Box 11, Folder 98)
  - Internet Folklore
    - Internet humor, 45 pages (Box 11, Folder 99)
    - Internet images, 70 pages (Box 11, Folder 100)
    - Internet memorials, 35 pages (Box 11, Folder 101)
    - Internet numerology and coincidences, 35 pages (Box 11, Folder 102)
    - Internet urban legends/rumors, 35 pages (Box 11, Folder 103)
    - Internet warnings, 15 pages (Box 11, Folder 104)
  - Clippings and Online Articles
    - Library of Congress Publications, 55 pages (Box 11, Folder 105)
      Clippings about the September 11, 2001 Documentary Project
    - Media Clippings about the September 11, 2001 Documentary Project, 55 pages (Box 11, Folder 106)
    - Media Clippings about September 11, 2001, 65 pages (Box 11, Folder 107)
    - Stampa Generale S.R.L. Benvenuti A Napoli. Naples, Italy: SG S.r.l., 2001, 65 pages (Box 12, Folder 108)
      (A magazine published by a private firm in colloboration with the Naples Military Community). Sent in by Scott E. George (See SR382-385).
    - Enterprise Record (Chico, California). Sent in by Michael Reinschmidt., 65 pages (Box 12, Folder 109)
      (See Reports subseries in Manuscripts)